Nicole: OSINT or open-source intelligence
is information that comes from publicly
available sources, that can be accessed
by the use of internet resources.
These sources can be from television,
newspaper articles, research papers
and industry journals, census and
public record data, business and
trade documents, blogs and social
media posts, websites and more.
Abraham: Some of this data can
be found just by a simple google
search, some search for much harder
to find information, that is not
found on normal search engines, and
these can include database, image,
and deep and dark web searches.
But as there is so much information
to go through, and so many different
sources, where do they start?
Nicole: When cyber security professionals
search for ‘open-source intelligence’
they are usually searching for
specific sources of information, and
often use advanced search functions,
specialist software tools and websites.
Collecting and analysing data
gathered from these open sources
can produce actionable intelligence.
It can be used for national security,
law enforcement, business intelligence
and is of value to a wide range
of cyber security professionals,
such as intelligence analysts.
Abraham: OSINT can be used for many
different things including ‘Counter
Terrorism’, ‘Violent Extremist Threat
Monitoring’, ‘Security Vetting’,
‘fraud and financial crime detection’,
‘organised crime and trafficking
detection’ and corporate security.
So why is it important to only use
reliable and valid sources of Open
Source Intelligence information?
Nicole: With so much Open Source
Intelligence information available,
cyber security professionals need
to make sure that their sources of
information are both reliable and valid.
Accessing and using unreliable sources
and inaccurate data can mean they
may be wasting time in searching
through information that is invalid,
out of date or totally wrong.
It may even involve chasing
false leads and missing relevant
vulnerabilities and threats.
Abraham: Inaccurate sources of
information can also cause serious
problems for organisations and
sometimes for other people.
Imagine someone being falsely
identified or falsely accused.
This can lead to serious legal
issues, including large fines,
for breaches of the GDPR laws.
Nicole: Although OSINT is readily and
publicly available, the use of it and its
storage and processing is subject to GDPR
or General Data Protection Regulation, and
any business or organisation using it must
adhere to the GDPR rules and regulations.
This includes safeguarding that
information from cyber attack and having
permission to process any personal data.
Abraham: One thing everyone should
think about is that data is considered
publicly available on social media, when
it is accessible not just to personal
contacts or friends but to everyone.
SOCMINT or social media intelligence
is a form of OSINT that is often
used by companies and organisations
when hiring or firing employees for
something they have posted online.
But remember threat actors also
have access to that data and
they don’t care about GDPR.
Nicole: So as we have said OSINT is
a valuable tool for cyber security
professionals and it stands to reason that
is also a valuable tool to threat actors.
They can use OSINT tools and techniques to
search for and identify potential targets.
This is why many small companies
and individuals, get hacked
because of all the OSINT, and the
vulnerabilities in their systems.
Remember threat actors can track
online activities, as do social
media sites and they have all the
information on how users reach a site.
Internet users need to be aware that their
research activity can be used to inform
others so should therefore be kept hidden.
Abraham: OSINT in general can involve
a large amount of input from people
to verify the validity of information.
There is a potential for overload and
therefore the right tools are needed to
filter out the ‘noise’ or irrelevancies.
However, relying on OSINT doesn’t remove
the need for traditional intelligence
gathering as they both should be used
in conjunction to get the best results.
So, what happens if in general reliable
sources of information are not used?
Nicole: As we all know technology
is constantly changing and new
threats are also constantly emerging.
To make sure the intelligence about those
threats is reliable the source of the
information also needs to be reliable.
Unreliable sources can often lead
to false information in the form of
false positives and false negatives.
Abraham: What are false positives?
False positives are when a threat is
seen to be there, but it isn’t real.
Investigating this can involve cyber
security teams in wasting many hours
and resources and may also distract from
seeing and following up a real threat.
Nicole: What are false negatives?
False negatives lead cyber security
professionals to believe there is no
threat, when there is, or overlook a
threat that that may not seem dangerous.
This could reduce the ability
of the security team to respond
to or minimise an attack when it
happens as they are not prepared.
A false negative could also be part of
hiding a more sophisticated attack which
is capable of evading early detection
therefore making it less preventable.